Hello, and welcome to Lesson 7 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
您好，欢迎来到Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第7课。
Our topic for today is derivatives and rates of change.
今天我们的主题是导数工具和变化率。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson. At the start, we said that
让我们从今天课程的简要概述开始。
calculus is the science of change. The primary goal of calculus is to study change.
首先，我们说微积分是变化的科学。 微积分的主要目标是研究变化。
Now there is one way to study change, and that’s to use functions. Functions tell us
现在有一种研究变化的方法，那就是使用函数。
how one quantity changes with respect to other quantities. For example, here’s a function
函数告诉我们一个数量相对于其他数量如何变化。 例如，这是一个函数
which relates x to f[x] or y, and that’s the plot of the function. That tells you
将 x 与 f[x] 或 y 关联起来，这是函数图。
how y changes with respect to x, but of course we need more than that often.
图像告诉您 y 对于 x 如何变化，但是我们当然需要的比这更多。
We need to know how the function changes with point to point. We need the rate of change,
我们需要知道函数点到点的变化。可以这么说，我们需要变化率。
so to speak. If you have a straight line, that’s simple; you simply find the slope.
如果您有一条直线，那很简单, 您只需找到斜率即可。
Here’s a straight line, the slope is 3, and that’s a very nice measure of
这是一条直线，斜率是3，这是对该函数变化率的很好衡量。
the rate of change of that function. In this lesson, we’ll show you how to do that
在本课程中，我们将向您展示如何对更多的函数
for more general functions. In other words, we’ll try and generalize the idea of slope
做到这一点, 换句话说，我们将尝试使用所谓的导数来概括斜率的概念。
using what are known as derivatives. That’s the theme for today, derivatives and rates of change.
这就是今天的主题，导数工具和变化率。
Let’s begin with the notion of a derivative. The derivative is a special kind of limit, and that limit,
让我们从导数概念开始。
roughly speaking, is linked to the tangent to a curve. I haven’t told exactly how,
导数是一种特殊的极限，从广义上讲，该极限与曲线的切线相关。我还没说清楚
but we’ll see that later. For example, if you have a straight line, the simplest kind of curve,
但我们稍后会看到。例如，如果您有一条直线（最简单的曲线）
then the slope of the straight line is rise over run. That’s difference in y over difference in x,
则直线的斜率是 Rise 比 Run。分别是 y 与 x 的变化值，
and in the f notation, that’s f(x) − f(a) over x − a. The question is,
在一般函数 f 中，它是 f(x) − f(a) 比 x − a
is that good enough for a general function f, and the answer is no. This only gives you
问题是，对于一般函数 f 这个比值是否足够好，答案是否定的。 这只会给你
the slope of the secant line for an arbitrary function f. Let’s see that.
函数 f 的割线的斜率。 让我们看看。
Here’s a function f[x] = 1/x, a very simple function, and let’s take two points on it, (1/2, 2) and (3, 1/3),
这是一个函数 f[x] = 1/x，这是一个非常简单的函数，让我们对它取两点，(1/2, 2) 和 (3, 1/3),
and work out the slope of the secant line between those two points. That’s −2/3.
并计算出这两点之间的割线斜率。 是 −2/3。
Now if you draw the graph of the function and that secant line, you see it’s not quite what we need.
现在，如果您绘制函数图和该割线，就会发现它并不是我们所需要的。
It’s just a little too far off to be useful. What’s missing over here is that the two points
它还缺乏实用性。这里欠缺的是，
need to be really close by, and so really what we need is the notion of limits that we studied earlier on.
这两个点需要非常接近，因此我们真正需要的是我们先前研究的极限的概念。
To find the tangent line to a curve at a point, you really need to take the limit of secant lines.
要找到一条曲线的切线，您确实需要采用割线的极限。
To be more precise, you need to find the difference in f between x and a
更准确地说，您需要找到 x 和 a 之间的函数值 f 的差值
over the difference in x itself, and then take the limit as x approaches the given point a.
与 x 差值的比值，然后取 x 在给定点 a 处的极限。
This is what will give you the slope of the tangent line that goes through the required point (a, f[a]).
这将给出过一给定点 (a, f[a]) 的切线的斜率
Here’s an example to show you that you have a secant line over here, and then as you let
这是一个示例，向您展示在这里有一条割线，
the points come closer and closer, you will then get the tangent line.
然后随着点越来越近，您将得到切线。
It’s only in the limit that you actually get the tangent line starting from a secant line.
实际上只有从割线出发求极限才能真正得到切线。
Okay. As an example of a tangent line, let’s take the curve of f[x] = x^3, and here’s a slope of
好的。 作为一个切线的例子，让我们以曲线 f[x] = x^3
the secant line through the point (1, 1) and the limit, and that’s the slope of the tangent.
为例，这是过点 (1, 1) 的割线的斜率极其极限值，也就是切线的斜率。
If the slope is 3, then the equation is y − y1 equal to slope times (x − x1), and if you plot that,
如果斜率是 3，则方程为 y − y1 = 斜率乘 (x − x1)
you surely do get the tangent line to the curve x^3 at this point (1, 1). Just to summarize,
画图，就可以确定在点（1，1）处与曲线 x^3 的切线。 总结一下，
given a point on a curve, what you do first is you work out the limit of this quotient over here.
给定曲线上的一个点，首先要做的是在此计算商的极限。
You get the slope. That slope can be used to find the equation of the line, and that line
你得到了斜率。 该斜率可用于确定一条直线的方程，然后该直线就是切线。
is then the tangent line. It’s slope times (x − x1) + y1 in this plot over here.
在此图中，它是斜率乘 (x − x1) + y1。
Okay. In practice, of course, we use something called the difference quotient to find derivatives.
好的。 当然，实际上，我们使用所谓的差商来计算导数。
Here’s the difference quotient, but it says you want the limit as this number h approaches 0
这是差商，但它表示在 h 趋于 0 时,
of the difference between f at a nearby point and at the given point over h.
在给定点 f 的函数值与相邻近一点的函数值的差与 h 的比值的极限
It’s still a slope, but it’s a slope in a slightly different form. As an example, suppose f[x] = 1/x.
它仍然是斜率，但形式略有不同。 例如，假设 f[x] = 1/x。
Work out the slope over here, and you get −1. Now once you’ve got the slope, what you can do is
算出这里的斜率，则得-1。现在，一旦有了斜率，您可以做的
you can plug in and find the equation of the tangent line, and here you are.
就是代入并找到切线的方程式，就可以了。
That is the correct tangent line at the point.
那是该点的正确切线。
Okay. Now a couple of places where you might find this notion. First of all, the idea of velocity.
好的。 现在在几个地方可以有这个概念的对应。 首先是速度的概念。
The instantaneous velocity of a position function is given by the slope of a tangent line
位置函数的瞬时速度由切线的斜率给出。
to the positional curve. If a particle is changing position and you want to find
如果粒子正在改变位置，而您想找到
the speed or the velocity at a particular time, then all you do is you work out the tangent line
一段时间的平均速度大小或特定时间点的速度，那么您要做的就是在该点上绘制曲线的切线。
to the curve at that point. For example, suppose that the position is this very simple function s[t] = 5t.
例如，假设位置函数是这个非常简单的函数 s[t] = 5 t。
You work out the velocity by doing the difference quotient calculation we did earlier on,
您通过执行我们之前做的差商计算出速度，
and then you find out that in fact the position is, in this case, a linear function
然后发现实际上在这种情况下位置是线性函数
while the velocity is constant, which of course we could have guessed from earlier work
虽然速度是恒定的，我们当然可以从早期
in your class on physics or other subjects. This is the notion of velocity as the derivative of position.
的物理或其他学科课程的知识中猜到。 这是速度的概念，它是位移的导数。
Okay. A slightly harder problem. Suppose a ball is dropped from a building 100 m above the ground,
好的。 一个稍微困难的问题。 假设有一个球从地面上方 100m
and you want to find the velocity of the ball after two seconds, let’s say,
的建筑物上掉下来，而您想两秒钟后求出球的速度，
and you want to find out how fast it’s going when the ball hits the ground.
并且您想找出当球击中地面时的速度。
There are two problems over here. You want to find what the velocity is after two seconds
这里有两个问题。
and you want to find out how fast it is going, the ball is going, when it hits the ground.
您想知道两秒钟后球的速度，想知道当球撞击地面时球的运动速度。
Now, you can work out the equation of motion as 100, the initial height, minus 4.9t^2—
现在，您可以写出运动方程为 初始高度为100 减去 4.9t^2，
that comes from the acceleration of gravity—and then what you can do is you can work out
它来自重力加速度，然后您可以做的是，可以使用差商计算出时间
the speed at time t = 2 by using the difference quotient calculation. Now the question is
t = 2 时的速度。 现在的问题是
why is it negative? It’s negative because the ball is going down. If you plot the position
为什么是负的？ 因为球正在下降。
and the tangent equation we saw just now, that’s the velocity over here. Okay. The question now is
如果您绘制位移函数和切线方程，就得到了速度。好的。 现在的问题是
what happens when the ball hits the ground? When the ball hits the ground, the displacement is 0.
当球撞击地面时会发生什么？ 当球撞击地面时，位移为 0。
You solve that equation, which just says that the displacement is 0 when the time is about 4.517.
您可以解该方程式，该方程式仅表示时间约为 4.517 时位移为 0。
Now you can plug into the derivative the speed, and you get back −44.2719.
现在您可以将速度带入导数，然后返回−44.2719。
That’s the way to find out what happens to the ball when it hits the ground, what the speed is.
这是找出球撞击地面时会发生什么情况，也就是求速度的方法。
Okay. Now the question is what is the slope of the tangent line at a point?
好的。 现在的问题是切线在一点处的斜率是多少？
Well, it is the derivative at that point. When people say derivative at a point, what they really mean is
是那时的导数。当人们在某一点说导数时，它们的真正含义是
the slope of the tangent line and vice versa. Now we have a shorthand for it.
切线的斜率，反之亦然。现在我们有一个简写。
We use the notation f'[x] over there. If you say f[x] = x^3, then in the Wolfram Language,
我们使用符号 f'[x]。 如果您定义 f[x] = x^3，那么在Wolfram语言中，
f'[1] is the derivative at x = 1. The derivative of x^3 at (1, 1) is 3.
f'[1] 是 x = 1 的导数。x^3 在 (1, 1) 点的导数是3。
You can plot that and check that it in fact is the correct answer.
您可以对其进行绘图，并检查它是否确实是正确的答案。
A couple of more concepts over here. First of all, we have a notion of a tangent line
这里还有另外两个概念。
to a more general curve like over here. You’ve got the tangent line to a parabola,
首先，我们有一条切线与更一般的曲线相切的概念。你有一条抛物线的切线，
and you want to work out a tangent equation for that parabola. What you do is
并且您想为该抛物线求切线方程。 你要做的是
you set up an equation, which is y equal to slope, the derivative, times x − x1 plus y1,
您定义一个函数，该函数是 y 等于斜率, 或者说是导数乘以  x − x1 加 y1
and you work it out. Then you get actually the required plot of the parabola
回车运行。然后，您实际上得到了所需的抛物线图
with the tangent line at x = 2.
以及抛物线在 x = 2 处的切线图像。
Now sometimes people talk about the average rate of change. Suppose you’ve got a function y[x],
有时人们会讨论平均变化率。假设您有一个函数 y[x]，令 x
and let’s say x changes from x1 to x2. Naturally y changes from some y1 to y2.
从 x1 变化到 x2。自然，y 从 y1 变为 y2。
The increment over here means that change in x, and the increment over there means the change in y,
此处的增量表示 x的变化，而那里的增量表示y
so you’ve got Δx and Δy telling you what the change in x and the change in y are.
的变化，因此您得到了Δx 和 Δy 表示 x 的变化和 y的变化。
Their ratio is what is called the average rate of change of y with respect to x, as you go from x1 to x2.
它们的比值就是所谓的 y 相对于 x 的平均变化率。
This average rate of change is exactly the slope of the secant line between the two points.
该平均变化率恰好是两点之间的割线的斜率。
For example, if you want to find the average rate of change over this interval, you simply find
例如，如果要查找此时间间隔内的平均变化率，则只需用
the difference in the function values divided by the difference in the x values, and you get back
函数值的差除以 x值的差，即可得到平均变化率。
the average rate. Here is a plot of the secant line along with the original curve.
这是割线和原始曲线的图像。
As the secant line goes closer to the point, then of course we get the instantaneous rate of change.
随着割线越来越接近该点，我们当然可以得到瞬时变化率。
The instantaneous rate of change is the change that you get when Δx, the change in x, goes to 0.
瞬时变化率是当 x 的变化 Δx 变为 0 时获得的变化。
That is exactly the slope of the tangent line at that point. In our case,
那就是该点处切线的斜率。
if we take the limit in the calculation, then you get back the tangent line at the point.
在我们的例子中，如果我们在计算中取极限，那么您将获得该点的切线。
The instantaneous rate of change is exactly the derivative of y at x.
瞬时变化率恰好是 y 在 x 处的导数。
Finally, an example involving tables. Here is the table showing the US national debt in billions
最后，一个涉及列表的示例。
between 1980 and 2015, measured at 5 year increments. Here’s a plot.
列表显示了 1980 年至 2015 年之间以 10 年为增量单位的十亿美元的美国国债。这是图像。
It’s clearly going up. The question is can you estimate the instantaneous rate of change at the year 2010?
函数显然上升了。 问题是您可以估计 2010 年的瞬时变化率吗？
As a first step, what you do is you make a piecewise function from it, because that lets you
第一步，您要做的是从中创建一个分段函数，因为这使您
you build the function starting from the data. You want to find the derivative,
可以从数据开始构建函数。您想要求导数，
so you set up the quotient like we did earlier on. You want to find 2010,
因此您像我们之前那样定义了差商。
so that’s where that comes from. Then you can kind of interpolate—in other words,
您想找到 2010，也就是我们所给定的点。然后，您可以进行插值-换句话说，
in other words, find an average of the values between 2005 and 2015, and that, roughly speaking,
求出2005年至2015年之间的平均价值，
is the instantaneous rate of change at 2010. Roughly speaking, the rate of increase of debt
大致来说，这是 2010 年的瞬时变化率。大致来说，债务的增长率是
is about 1.1 trillion dollars in the year 2010.
在 2010 年约为1.1万亿美元。
Okay. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson, and the point is that the derivative of a function
好的。我们到了今天的课程结尾，重点是函数的导数
is simply the slope of the function at that point. You can think of this derivative as being
简单地是函数在该点的斜率。您可以认为导数是
the limit of the slopes of secant lines. You start a secant line, then you take the limit,
割线斜率的极限。开始一条割线，然后取极限，然后得到切线的导数。
then you get the derivative of the tangent line. Now the derivative idea is very useful
现在导数的思想在很多地方非常有用
in lots of places, like we saw for speed and that kind of thing in physics, and also for calculating,
比如我们看到的速度和物理学中的一些概念，以及在计算方面,
let’s say, debt in economics. Often the only data you have is a table of values, in which case
比如说, 经济学中的债务。通常，您仅有的数据是值表，在这种情况下
you can approximate the derivative. The idea is that starting with a table of values,
您可以近似导数。这个想法是从一个值表开始,
you can find the approximate value, but of course you cannot calculate
您可以找到一个近似值，但是您当然不能计算
the exact value of the derivative. That’s the idea for today, the idea of a derivative
导数的确切值。 这就是今天的想法，导数的思想和变化率的概念。
and the notion of rate of change. In the next lesson, we’ll talk about the derivative itself
在下一课中，我们将讨论作为函数的
as being a function just like function that you start with. I’ll stop over here.
导数概念, 就像您一开始时使用的普通函数一样。 我在这结束本节课了。
Do go over today’s lesson, try the exercises and you should be in good shape for the next lesson,
请仔细阅读今天的课程，尝试练习，您应该在下一课中保持良好状态。
which is lesson number 8. Thank you.
下节课是第八课。谢谢。
(翻译: 秦晋 北京师范大学)